export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2008 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. In Ghana the law enforces all the following except",
A: "political stability",
B: "unity and peace",
C: "freedom of religion",
D: "sustainable development",
answer: "D. sustainable development",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. Which of the following is not an implication of the rule of law?",
A: "All legal services are rendered free of charge",
B: "There can be no imprisonment without trial",
C: "Everyone is entitled to fair trial",
D: "No individual is above the law",
answer: "A. All legal services are rendered free of charge",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. The acceptable way of doing things in society is referred to as",
A: "rule of law",
B: "convention",
C: "constitution",
D: "rights",
answer: "B. convention",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. Laws that contravene the provisions of the constitution of a country are described as",
A: "Illegitimate",
B: "unconventional",
C: "Ineligible",
D: "arbitrary",
answer: "A. Illegitimate",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. The principle of citizenship determines who",
A: "qualifies to live in a state",
B: "is a legal member of the state",
C: "enjoys the privileges of living in a state",
D: "has to obey the laws of the state",
answer: "C. enjoys the privileges of living in a state",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. In Ghana when a person is arrested and detained for 72 hours the one is denied the right to",
A: "freedom of speech",
B: "freedom of assembly",
C: "personal liberty",
D: "freedom of movement",
answer: "C. personal liberty",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. The right to vote in society helps",
A: "individuals to participate in decision-making",
B: "in the delegation of public duties",
C: "to hasten economic development",
D: "to unite ethnic groups",
answer: "A. individuals to participate in decision-making",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. In the Ghanaian society, it is a duty of the citizen to",
A: "belong to a religious group",
B: "give charity to the needy",
C: "join a political party",
D: "protect public property",
answer: "D. protect public property",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. Persons who emerge as leaders in the midst of crisis are described as",
A: "Charismatic",
B: "Democratic",
C: "Situational",
D: "Autocratic",
answer: "C. Situational",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. To achieve the goals and aspirations of followers, the leader must, above all have",
A: "Self-control",
B: "vision and foresight",
C: "an attractive personality",
D: "support from the youth",
answer: "B. vision and foresight",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. In modern times, it is impossible to practice direct democracy because",
A: "those in opposition undermine the government",
B: "ruling parties satisfy only their followers",
C: "countries have grown in size and population",
D: "the rule of law does not allow it",
answer: "C. countries have grown in size and population",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. Which of the following is not a function of the judicial organ of government?",
A: "Proposing new laws",
B: "Dispensing justice",
C: "Settling disputes",
D: "Interpreting the law",
answer: "A. Proposing new laws",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. In Ghana, the executive power of the state is vested in the",
A: "Chief Justice",
B: "Speaker of parliament",
C: "Clerk of parliament",
D: "President",
answer: "D. President",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. The practice whereby a woman has more than one husband is referred to as",
A: "Polygyny",
B: "monogyny",
C: "Polyandry",
D: "polygamy",
answer: "C. Polyandry",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. The major function of the family is to",
A: "ensure continuity of membership through procreation",
B: "teach the norms and values of society",
C: "provide a sense of security for its members",
D: "provide unity and peace in society",
answer: "A. ensure continuity of membership through procreation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. Which of the following forms of marriage is approved under the Ordinance?",
A: "Monogamous",
B: "Polygamous",
C: "Polygynous",
D: "Bigamous",
answer: "A. Monogamous",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. A person’s unique character is known as",
A: "the ego",
B: "personality",
C: "the ideal self",
D: "heredity",
answer: "B. personality",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. In Abraham Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, hunger, thirst and air are classified as",
A: "Self-actualization",
B: "esteem",
C: "Physiological",
D: "love",
answer: "C. Physiological",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. The concept of self-identity implies",
A: "heredity traits",
B: "acquisition of skills",
C: "physical appearance",
D: "awareness of oneself",
answer: "D. awareness of oneself",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. The main duty of the police service",
A: "punish criminals",
B: "maintain law and order",
C: "protect state dignitaries",
D: "prevent external aggression",
answer: "B. maintain law and order",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. The most effective way of checking moral degeneration among the youth in Ghana is to",
A: "institute appropriate sanctions for wrong behaviour",
B: "reward well-behaved individuals",
C: "introduce guidance and counselling in the society",
D: "create more jobs to keep them busy.",
answer: "C. introduce guidance and counselling in the society",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. All the following are secondary agencies of socialization except the",
A: "school",
B: "church",
C: "community",
D: "family",
answer: "D. family",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. The values and customs passed on to a people from one generation to the other are referred to as",
A: "Convention",
B: "Folklore",
C: "Heritage",
D: "Lineage",
answer: "B. folklore",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. The major reason for the promotion of socio-cultural practices is to help",
A: "individuals to know themselves",
B: "solve problems of human interaction",
C: "identify individual psychological problems",
D: "prevent foreign influence",
answer: "B. solve problems of human interaction",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. Which of the following qualifies a society that constantly undergoes change in its ideas and practices?",
A: "Dynamic",
B: "Hardworking",
C: "Aggressive",
D: "Unstable",
answer: "A. Dynamic",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. All the following show how the environment controls human activities except",
A: "farming based on rainfall",
B: "the sea eroding the land",
C: "farming based on irrigation",
D: "siting settlements near rivers",
answer: "C. farming based on irrigation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. The immediate outcome of the depletion of the ozone layer is",
A: "frequent earthquakes",
B: "general global waning",
C: "rapid desertification",
D: "atmospheric pollution",
answer: "B. general global warming",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. All the following are advantages of forest reserves except",
A: "protection of watershed",
B: "protection of animal species",
C: "preservation of natural resource",
D: "improvement in foreign exchange earnings",
answer: "D. improvement in foreign exchange earnings",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. The line of descent of a family is known",
A: "lineage",
B: "hereditary",
C: "Patrilineal",
D: "matrilineal",
answer: "A. lineage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. The aged are respected in Ghanaian traditional society because it is believed they are",
A: "full of generosity",
B: "very close to the gods",
C: "associated with wisdom",
D: "known for good behaviour",
answer: "C. associated with wisdom",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. Which of the following is not a necessary qualification for one to become an ancestor?",
A: "Having children of your own",
B: "Exhibiting powers of oratory",
C: "Living an exemplary life",
D: "Dying a natural death",
answer: "B. Exhibiting powers of oratory",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. Which of the following statements explains a taboo?",
A: "Behaviour forbidden in society",
B: "Sanction imposed on a deviant",
C: "An act to pacify the gods",
D: "Making the gods angry",
answer: "A. Behaviour forbidden in society",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. Family life education can be described preparation for",
A: "Parenthood",
B: "childhood development",
C: "independent living",
D: "emotional growth",
answer: "A. Parenthood",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. The period of adolescence is characterized by",
A: "a feeling of low self-esteem",
B: "moving from childhood to adulthood",
C: "ability to take good care of the body",
D: "preparation for marriage",
answer: "B. moving from childhood to adulthood",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. The most serious economic effect of the spread of HIV/AIDS in Ghana is",
A: "high cost of education",
B: "high government expenditure on welfare",
C: "loss of human resource",
D: "reduction in government revenue",
answer: "C. loss of human resource",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. The surroundings within which human beings and plants live is referred to",
A: "social environment",
B: "cultural environment",
C: "socio-cultural environment",
D: "physical environment",
answer: "D. physical environment",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. The parenting style which encourages the best parent-child relationship is",
A: "authoritarian",
B: "democratic",
C: "permissive",
D: "paternalistic",
answer: "D. paternalistic",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. In which of the following types of education is teaching and learning an unconscious activity?",
A: "Formal education",
B: "Non-formal education",
C: "Moral education",
D: "Informal education",
answer: "D. Informal education",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. A gradual reduction in the quality of resources in the environment is referred to",
A: "Deforestation",
B: "Desertification",
C: "Degradation",
D: "Leaching",
answer: "C. Degradation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. Global warming is caused by",
A: "changes in the position of the planets",
B: "inadequate rainfall throughout the earth",
C: "the position of the equator in relation to the sun",
D: "emission of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere",
answer: "D. emission of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. The capacity of the Ghanaian to invest has generally been hampered by",
A: "high population growth and high dependency ratio",
B: "low population growth and low dependency ratio",
C: "low investment opportunities in the country",
D: "lack of initiative on the part of the people",
answer: "A. high population growth and high dependency ratio",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. The youthful nature of Ghana’s population implies",
A: "more efficient labour",
B: "high taxation for citizens",
C: "high dependency burden",
D: "optimum production capacity",
answer: "C. high dependency burden",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. The main focus of Ghana’s population policy is to",
A: "reduce birth rate",
B: "make people aware that the country is overpopulated",
C: "create awareness of the consequences of rapid population growth",
D: "educate the citizenry about contraception",
answer: "C. create awareness of the consequences of rapid population growth",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. The feeling that one’s cultural beliefs and practices are superior to those of other people is known as",
A: "egocentrism",
B: "ethnocentrism",
C: "eccentricity",
D: "fanaticism",
answer: "B. ethnocentrism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. Tourists are attracted to Ghana mostly by the country’s",
A: "climate",
B: "game and wildlife",
C: "rich cultural heritage",
D: "highlands",
answer: "C. rich cultural heritage",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. Which of the following is depicted by the national symbols of Ghana?",
A: "The physical strength of the ancestors",
B: "The ethnic diversity of the nation",
C: "The geographical size of the country",
D: "The national integration and unity of the people",
answer: "D. The national integration and unity of the people",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. In Ghana, which of the following cultural practices clearly indicates the identity of each ethnic group?",
A: "Music and dance",
B: "Code of dressing",
C: "Family life",
D: "System of diet",
answer: "A. Music and dance",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. In Ghana, all national flags fly at half-mast when there is a",
A: "Referendum",
B: "state of mourning",
C: "national anniversary",
D: "state of emergency",
answer: "B. state of mourning",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. All the following are true of the local government system in Ghana except",
A: "discussing plans for development",
B: "encouraging community projects",
C: "paying salaries of District Assembly members",
D: "receiving funds from the central government",
answer: "A. discussing plans for development",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. To develop good interpersonal relationships among members of a community attention must be paid to",
A: "economic ambitions of each individual",
B: "the bye-laws of the traditional council",
C: "existing social principles and norms",
D: "the family background of each person",
answer: "D. the family background of each person",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question51",
question: "51. Multilateral aid to Ghana comes mainly from",
A: "African Development Bank and International Finance Corporation",
B: "Germany and USA",
C: "China and Japan",
D: "International Monetary Fund and World Bank",
answer: "D. International Monetary Fund and World Bank",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question52",
question: "52. Ghana is a member of all the following international organizations except the",
A: "North Atlantic Treaty Organization",
B: "Commonwealth of Nations",
C: "United Nations Organization",
D: "Non-aligned Movement",
answer: "A. North Atlantic Treaty Organization",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question53",
question: "53. The main goal of national development is to",
A: "expand the export base of the country",
B: "raise the standard of living of the people",
C: "ensure good governance",
D: "create job opportunities",
answer: "B. raise the standard of living of the people",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question54",
question: "54. Scientific knowledge is based on",
A: "assumption",
B: "intuition",
C: "tested facts",
D: "technology",
answer: "C. tested facts",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question55",
question: "55. In a business enterprise, the profit made after subtracting expenses from revenue earned is known as",
A: "Net",
B: "Gross",
C: "Surplus",
D: "Reward",
answer: "A. Net",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question56",
question: "56. Which of the following resources is the most important to a country’s development?",
A: "Capital",
B: "Human",
C: "Natural",
D: "Aid",
answer: "B. Human",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question57",
question: "57. One effect of trade liberalization in Ghana is",
A: "the presence of more foreigners in the country",
B: "increase in the supply of locally manufactured goods",
C: "abundance of inferior goods on the market",
D: "foreign interference in government activities",
answer: "C. abundance of inferior goods on the market",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question58",
question: "58. Which of the following can be described as a secondary economic activity?",
A: "Mining",
B: "Baking",
C: "Farming",
D: "Teaching",
answer: "B. Baking",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question59",
question: "59. The main aim of setting up a public corporation is to  make profit for the government",
A: "provide essential services to the people",
B: "create employment for all people",
C: "compete with private enterprise",
},

{
id: "question60",
question: "60. The accounting officer records cash and bank transactions in a document called",
A: "Cashbook",
B: "Sales Day Book",
C: "Purchase Day Book",
D: "Ledger",
answer: "A. Cashbook",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]